<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four grand questions proposed, and briefly answered wherein is discoursed, the authority and duty of the magistrate in the matters of religion, the unlawfulness of a toleration and general liberty of conscience, the divine right of Christian liberty in things indifferent, the unlawfulness of repealing the laws against Popery and idolatry.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 915:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Four grand questions proposed, and briefly answered wherein is discoursed, the authority and duty of the magistrate in the matters of religion, the unlawfulness of a toleration and general liberty of conscience, the divine right of Christian liberty in things indifferent, the unlawfulness of repealing the laws against Popery and idolatry.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57754:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57754:1"/>
            <p>FOUR GRAND QUESTIONS PROPOSED, And Briefly ANSWERED. Wherein is Diſcourſed,
<list>
                  <item>The Authority and Duty of the Magiſtrate in the Matters of <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGION.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Unlawfulneſs of a Toleration and General Liberty of Conſcience.</item>
                  <item>The Divine Right of Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Things Indifferent.</item>
                  <item>The Unlawfulneſs of Repealing the Laws againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the YEAR, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:57754:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57754:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT cannot but be generally underſtood, what an abundance of Heats and Animoſtties have been raiſed in the Nation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a <hi>Toleration, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Laws about Religion,</hi> which have been pleaded for by many, whether with greater vehemency, or with greater abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is hard to ſay; for the Lawfulneſs of it hath rather been ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed than proved by any: For whilſt they have been conſidering how to ſecure a Toleration, and Repeal the Laws that eſtabliſh Religion, they never conſidered, Whether it could be conſiſtent with the Office and Duty of the <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtracy,</hi> to do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one or the other. Tho' ſuch a Toleration and Repealing the Laws doth carry in it nothing leſs, than an Exemption from the Obligation of all Humane Laws in the Matters of Religion; which muſt neceſſarily ſuppoſe no Authority nor Duty incumbent on the Chriſtian Magiſtracy, to take Care for True Religion and the Worſhip of God; which, if that could be proved, would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſtrongeſt Arguments of all for a Toleration and Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Laws; and unleſs that could be proved, whatever Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments elſe may be brought for it, from other Reſpects and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, they are of no Force, if this be taken for granted, That 'tis againſt the Duty incumbent on the Government, by the Law of God to do it. And tho' there are indeed weighty Arguments againſt ſuch a Toleration and Repealing the Laws, drawn from the ill Effects, Means &amp; Ends of it; yet this Argument ſeems to be moſt cogent, and of greateſt force, that is drawnfrom the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and principal Cauſe why 'tis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful, namely, Being againſt the Office and Duty of the <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57754:3"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Principle therefore I have alwaies been perſwaded, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at not only a general Toleration, but Repealing the Laws, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orally <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful, unleſs better Laws could be made by the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> to Secure Religion; which no man of Senſe can think, unleſs ſuch Laws have alſo a <hi>Penalty;</hi> for, What Force or Obligation can Laws have to this End, without a <hi>Penalty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have therefore in this little Treatiſe, under the following Queſtions, (as compendiouſly as poſſible) proved the Magiſtrate's Office and Duty about <hi>Religion,</hi> to be Moral and Perpetual, and not belonging to the Old Teſtament Adminiſtration; only from this, as a Principle, I have argued the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of a general <hi>Toleration,</hi> and of ſuch a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> as is oppoſed to all Humane Authority and Laws in the matters of Religion; yet nevertheleſs, leſt any ſhould hence conclude, That a Humane Authority can impoſe Laws on the Church, in things of Religion not neceſſary, or commanded by the Word of <hi>GOD;</hi> I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Divine Right of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> in things Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, eſpecially if the ſame Indifferences be matter of Doubt or Scandal; and, That the practice of ſuch a Liberty in Religion in things Indifferent, tho' reſtrained by Laws, is no matter of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> given, nor any Aſſent to a general Toleration, or the <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power:</hi> And in the laſt place I have proved the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Repealing the Laws againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and Anſwered the moſt ſpecious Pretences alledged for it.</p>
            <p>If that which is here briefly diſcourſed may obtain its deſigned end, to ſet the Judgments of ſome men right, in thoſe great and weighty points, the Author will have his end in expoſing the ſame to publick view, which was firſt compoſed for his own ſatisfaction.</p>
            <trailer>Now to the King-Eternal, Immortal, Inviſible, the only Wiſe God, be Honour and Glory for ever and ever <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57754:3"/>
            <head>Four Grand QUESTIONS pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and Briefly Anſwered; <hi>(VIZ.)</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>I. Whether it be the Duty of Magiſtrates under the Goſpel, to promote and preſerve by Laws the True <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. Whether it be lawful for the Chriſtian Magiſtrate to give a general Toleration of All Religions; or, what Liberty in Religion he ought to Allow.</item>
                  <item>III. Whether it be lawful for Subjects to give their Actual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a general Toleration.</item>
                  <item>IV. Whether it be lawful for Subjects to Conſent to the Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theſe Laws, that Eſtabliſh and Preſerve the True Religion.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head>Of Theſe in Order.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>I. Whether it be the Duty of Magiſtrates under the Goſpel, to promote and preſerve by Laws the True Chriſtian Religion.</head>
               <p>BUt before we proceed, it will be neceſſary to lay down, by way of Suppoſition, what we underſtand by <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> and what by the <hi>True Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here we ſhall not meddle with the divers Forms of Lawful Government, but reſt ſatisfied, that our own form of Government is either Beſt in it ſelf conſidered, or at leaſt Beſt for us.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57754:4"/>
               <p>By <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> therefore we underſtand chiefly the Supreme Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power of a Nation, or of a Body politick, not excluding Subordinate Magiſtrates alſo within their reſpective limits.</p>
               <p>By the <hi>True Chriſtian Religion,</hi> we underſtand the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> in thoſe eſſential matters of Proteſtant Faith, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, wherein it is truly ſuch.</p>
               <p>Now, that the Office of Magiſtracy is founded, both in the Law of Nature, the Moral Law, and alſo is of a Divine Inſtitution, by the poſitive Command of God, I take for a granted Truth, and will be denyed but by few: All the Queſtion then before us is, About the Extent of the Magiſtrates Power: Some will have it now <hi>under the Goſpel,</hi> to reſpect only Civil Matters and Moral Juſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Men, but that he hath no Authority in the Inſtitutions of Reveal'd Religion under the Goſpel. Hence it would follow, that he is not oblig'd to maintain by Laws the Goſpel-Inſtitutions. But the Affirmative is that which I undertake to make good, and that by the following Arguments.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. From the Efficient Cauſe of Magiſtracy.</item>
                  <item>2. From the Formal Cauſe of Magiſtracy.</item>
                  <item>3. From the Final Cauſe or End of Magiſtracy.</item>
                  <item>4. From Scripture-Precept, and Precedent.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That 'tis the Duty of Magiſtrates to promote and preſerve by Laws the True Chriſtian Religion,</hi> will appear from the conſideration of the Efficient Cauſe of Magiſtracy, which is no other than God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Now God may be ſaid to be the Cauſe, and ſo the Author, of Magiſtracy, in a threefold reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> By his Law Natural, Moral, and Poſitive.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By his Law Natural, implanted and written in the Heart of Man, by which Mankind is enabled to know and underſtand both the reaſonableneſs, neceſſity, and utility of Political Government, in order to promote and preſerve the good of Societies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By his Law Moral, thus the Fifth Commandment eſtabliſneth the Relation, and enjoineth the Duties between political Fathers and Subjects, as well as between natural Parents and their Children.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is alſo the Cauſe of Magiſtracy, by his poſitive Ordinance and Appointment: Thus he appointed Magiſtrates, both Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Extraordinary, under the Old Teſtament: And we find
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57754:4"/> alſo the Office and Power of Magiſtracy ratified and confirmed by the New Teſtament, <hi>under the Goſpel;</hi> the Apoſtle tells us, That all Powers are of God, and that not only by his providential Allowance and Toleration, but by his ſpecial Aſſignation and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment; therefore ſaid to be ordained of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2. &amp; therefore the Magiſtrate is ſaid to be the Miniſter of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. Hence we find that all that Juſtice which the Magiſtrate executeth, is called the Juſtice of God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 6. They are alſo called <hi>Gods, Pſal.</hi> 82. 1, 6. becauſe they are God's Deputies and Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, repreſenting his Preſence and his Power in the World.</p>
               <p>Now it cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed, that God would thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate his Power and Authority in the World to Magiſtrates, and ſo ſignally dignifie and authoriſe them, but in order to ſome ſpecial Service they are to do for God in the World: And 'tis moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and morally juſt, that the Magiſtrate having his Power and Authority from God, he ſhould imploy it beſt for his Service in the World, which he cannot do, but by promoting and maintaining True Religion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This will further appear from the conſideration of the formal Cauſe of Magiſtracy, to wit, The <hi>Laws;</hi> for 'tis the <hi>Law</hi> that giveth Form and Being to the Magiſtrate, and is the life and ſoul of Government. Hence are thoſe Axioms, <hi>Lex facit Regem,—Rex nihil poteſt, niſi quod jure poteſt.</hi> Now Laws do originally derive all their force from Religion, becauſe the Moral Law of God is the Supream Law of all Nations, and therefore the Ground and Rule of all Humane Laws; which Law of God, we ſee, doth in the firſt place take care for Religion and the Worſhip of God, as the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and ground of all Duties of Moral Juſtice between men. Our Saviour tells us, That the firſt and great Commandment of the Law is, to <hi>love the Lord our God with all our heart, ſoul, ſtrength, and mind, Luk.</hi> 10. 27. which doth indeed include and preſcribe the moſt exact way of Religion and Holineſs that can be.</p>
               <p>Now this Divine Law being both the Foundation and Directory, of all other Laws, it muſt therefore follow, That all Humane Laws by which Magiſtrates ought to Govern, ſhould in the firſt place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for True Religion and the Worſhip of God; for the Moral Law of God being the Supream Law, and Rule of Life for all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, is therefore the Rule of all Laws and Government, and all, Humane Laws, that have the true nature of Laws, are grounded on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57754:5"/> it, or reducible to it, or elſe theyare but Tyrannical Impoſitions. Hence it is that the political Laws of Nations are ſaid to have a kind of Sacredneſs in them, which is to be underſtood when they are founded (as they ought to be) on the Principles of the Law of God, &amp; their Agreement thereunto giveth Force and Obligation to them; for the Obligation of Laws ariſeth from the good End they tend unto, and are uſeful for, in conjunction with the lawful Authority that impoſeth them.</p>
               <p>So that now the Law of God, being the Rule of humane Laws, whereunto they ought to correſpond in all the precepts thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively; it follows therefore, that the Laws of Magiſtrates, in conformity to the Law of God, which, we ſee, giveth the prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to firſt Table-Duties, ought alſo in the firſt place to provide for the Exerciſe of True Religion, and the Worſhip of God, as the ground of all other Laws that reſpect Moral Juſtice amongſt men.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, From the final Cauſe or End of Magiſtracy, which is threefold;
<list>
                     <item>1. The Glory of GOD.</item>
                     <item>2. The Good of Societies.</item>
                     <item>3. The Good of the Church.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Glory of God; which as it is the chief and ultimate end of Man, ſo of all God's Ordinances and Inſtitutions, for the ſake and good of Mankind, that in and by them the glory of God may be advanced: God then being the efficient Cauſe of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it therefore follows, that his Glory muſt be the principal End: now 'tis the proper End and Uſe of Religion, to give glory to God; and without the practice of true Religion, the Divine Perfections are not actually adored and advanced. If then the end of Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy be to advance and ſet up the glory of God in the World, he ought to ſet up and maintain True Religion, as the greateſt Glory can be brought to God in this World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The good of Societies is the ſubordinate End of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy; for as the Fundamental Humane Cauſes of Government is the Neceſſity of it for the Publick Good, ſo the End of Magiſtracy in that reſpect, is, that the Temporal Good and Tranquillity of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties may be promoted and preſerved.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57754:5"/>
               <p>Now, if there were no higher Cauſes and Ends of Magiſtracy than this, (as we have already, and ſhall further prove there is) yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, it would be the Duty of Magiſtrates to take care for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, becauſe 'tis very certain, that True Religion doth beſt of all conduce to the Temporal good of Societies: This is plain not only from the Scriptures, that aſſure us, that <hi>Godlineſs is profitable unto all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. but alſo from the reaſon and experience of Mankind. Therefore we ſee, that even in thoſe Nations that were void of the knowledge of True Religion, yet thoſe that were Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators and Governours amongſt them, alwaies with their Laws mixed ſome Precepts of Religion and Opinion of God, ſome preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they received their Laws from God himſelf. Whereby we ſee that they thought, that Laws and Government could not ſtand without ſomething of Religion; which tho' their religious Precepts were ſuperſtitious and idolatrous, in the want of Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet nevertheleſs it thence appears, That the Law of Nature taught them not only the neceſſity and obligation of Government and Laws, but alſo that the ſence of Religion was the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Foundation of it.</p>
               <p>And then it will follow, that if any thing of Religion be neceſſary for the temporal good of Governments, that the True Religion is then beſt of all, and moſt neceſſary, that being the Spring and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all Virtues, from whence is to be drawn, not only the beſt Directions for, but the ſtrongeſt Motives and Engagements unto all thoſe Duties of Moral Juſtice and Charity amongſt men, which are ſo abſolutely neceſſary, even to the temporal good of Societies. It would be eaſie to demonſtrate, that True Religion is certainly the beſt Foundation of all Political Government, and of the Execution of Laws, the Obedience of Subjects, and of the Exerciſe of that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Charity between men, which only can render the life of man peaceable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this World. If then the End of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and Civil Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ernment were only for the temporal good of Societies, yet it would follow, that 'tis the Duty of Magiſtrates, to advance and maintain True Religion, becauſe it chiefly conduceth, and is ſo neceſſary to this End.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, and laſtly,</hi> The Special End of Magiſtracy is for the good of the Church, and that becauſe Magiſtracy is not a meer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and humane Policy, but an Ordinance of God, ſtill remaining ſuch now under the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57754:6"/>
               <p>Now 'tis certain, that all the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of God, both Moral and Evangelical, do now in ſpecial belong to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Church; for whatever Advantages any of the Heathen World do receive at any time by any of Gods Ordinances and Inſtitutions, (as particularly by this of Magiſtracy) 'tis but for the ſake of the Church, as the Dogs eat of the Childrens Crumbs: For 'tis to be noted, That as the Scriptures. themſelves, ſo alſo all the Precepts, Promiſes, Rights, Priviledges, &amp; Ordinances, granted and confirmed thereby, or contained therein, belongs primarily and eſpecially to the Church of God. So that Magiſtracy then being an Ordinance of God, and having its Foundation in the Law and Word of God, it muſt follow, that the End of Magiſtracy is eſpecially for the ſake and good of the Church, and not only for the World.</p>
               <p>As for that lawful Magiſtracy that may be found in Heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or without the Viſible Church, the Power is truly ſaid to be from God, becauſe the Office of Magiſtracy is founded on his Law and Ordinance; but the Execution of this Power hath been and is in moſt Nations wickedly abuſed, and perverted from the proper and ſpecial Ends of it, appointed of God, to ſerve the Ambition, Tyranny, and Luſts of men; the ground and occaſion of which proceeds from the ſame common Original with all other Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in the life of man, to wit, the defection of mankind from God, and the depravity of the Humane Nature by Sin. But as 'tis therefore no wonder, that the Ends of Magiſtracy are perverted, eſpecially in thoſe Nations that have forſaken God and fallen to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry; ſo 'tis no Argument, that Magiſtracy is only for the world, as ſome ſuppoſe, and not eſpecially for the good of the Church.</p>
               <p>Thus we find, that to this end was Magiſtracy appointed by God under the Old Teſtament, but while the Church of God, in the firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the world, was but in ſmall Families, &amp; ſometime only in one Family; their Civil Government cannot ſo properly be called Political, belonging to a State or Common-wealth, as Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or the government of a Family: Yet we find, that then the care of Religion did belong to the Lord or Governour of the Family. And indeed, all lawful Government whatſoever being from <hi>GOD,</hi> doth carry in it an Obligation to the Care of Religion, for thoſe under their power. Thus <hi>God</hi> ſaith of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>I know him, that he will command his Children and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57754:6"/>
               <p>But when the Viſible Church of God, to wit, the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> was multiplied into a Body of People, and ſet at liberty, from the Yoke of <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Bondage, and ſo capable of being formed into a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Body or Common-wealth, God himſelf inſtituted an ordinary ſtate of Magiſtracy, to continue in all their gates, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 18. (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides extraordinary Magiſtrates from time to time, as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, &amp;c.</hi>) and to the Supream Magiſtrates eſpecially, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Care of the right Adminiſtration of Religion and the Worſhip of God, as well as of Civil Juſtice between men; by which Examples God himſelf teacheth us not only the neceſſity and obligation of having a Magiſtracy over a Body of People, but alſo the office and duty whereunto it ought to be applied.</p>
               <p>And tho' under the Goſpel all the Kings and Governours of the World were in the firſt Ages of the Chriſtian Church, and have been, for the moſt part, ever ſince Enemies to the Church, yet it doth not therefore follow, that becauſe they have thus perverted their power, that it ought not to have been applied for the Churches good, under the Goſpel; for we find that 'tis propheſied of Kings, and promiſed alſo to the Goſpel-Church, that <hi>Kings ſhall be her nurſing-Fathers, and Queens her nurſing-Mothers, Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. And this prediction and promiſe hath in it the force and obligation of a Command, upon all Kings and Magiſtrates in the World; not only to believe in Chriſt, but to become nurſing-Fathers to the Church; which Expreſſion cannot imply leſs in it, than to imploy their Power and Care, as Magiſtrates, to promote, ſuccour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Church. Hence Kings are exhorted to <hi>kiſs the Son, Pſ.</hi> 2. 12. which is a token of Homage and Subjection to Chriſt, who is now <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords, Rev.</hi> 19. 16. And <hi>all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth is given unto him, Mat.</hi> 28. 18. And therefore ſome would have all Magiſtratical Power to be derived from Chriſt, as he is Mediator of the Church.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if we conſider how much good pious and godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates may do to the Church, it will from thence further appear, That Magiſtracy, under the Goſpel, is for the good of the Church, as by promoting its Intereſt, preſerving its Priviledges and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, ſuppreſſing Hereſies, purging out Corruptions, oppoſing its Enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now we argue thus; that, If God hath made the Chriſt an Magiſtrate, by his power and place in the World, capable of doing ſo much good for the Church, 'tis certain then,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57754:7"/> that he is morally obliged to do it, for that every perſon, in his Place and Calling, is, for the ſake of the Church, to ſeek its Good. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. 9. <hi>Becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The laſt Argument to prove, that 'tis the Duty of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates under the Goſpel, to promote and preſerve True Religion, is drawn both from Scripture-precept and precedent.</p>
               <p>As for Scripture-Precept, we find, that by the Low of God, Sins againſt Religion and Divine Worſhip, which reſpect the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commands, were to be ſeverely puniſhed by the Magiſtrate. Thus the Blaſphemer was to be put to death, <hi>Lev.</hi> 24. 16. The falſe Prophetor Teacher, that would draw off any from the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, or him or her that committed Idolatry, were to be put to death; <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 9, 17. and the City that fell to Idolatry, was to be ſmitten with the edge of the Sword, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 15. Now the Magiſtrate bearing the Sword of Juſtice, and being the Avenger of God againſt evil doers, 'tis to be underſtood, that by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Direction this was to be done.</p>
               <p>And for Scripture-Precedent, we find, that thoſe that were godly Kings and Magiſtrates under the Old Teſtament, purged the Church from Idolatry, when corrupted, and reſtored the true Worſhip of God, cauſed both Prieſts and People to keep the Law of the Lord. Thus good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſuppreſſeth Idolatry, and ſetteth up the true Worſhip of God, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Joſias</hi> did the like, and ſlew all the Prieſts of the high places, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23. 20. <hi>Jehu</hi> deſtroyed all the Worſhippers of <hi>Baal,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 25. And King <hi>Aſa</hi> with the people made a Law, That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhould be put to death, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 13. And theſe are approv'd for ſo doing; whereas thoſe Kings that took no care of Religion, but did either ſet up Idolatry, or did not ſuppreſs it, are branded for ſuch as did evil in the ſight of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> But it will be objected, That what the Magiſtrate thus did under the Old Teſtament, for the Cauſe of Religion, was but the Execution of God's own Laws, which he was obliged to do, but that this is no Precedent for Chriſtian Magiſtrates under the Goſpel, becauſe thoſe Laws are now abrogated, and there are no new Laws preſcribed by God under the Goſpel, for the inflicting of any puniſhments, either pecuniary or corporal, for any Offences againſt Religion; and therefore the Magiſtrate hath no Authority to make Penal Laws for this end.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57754:7"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Tho' it be granted, That the Goſpel preſcribes no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for Offences againſt Religion; and that the Judicial Law alſo, as it was peculiar to that Nation, ſo is not preciſely binding on any Nation under the Goſpel; yet it will not therefore follow, that Magiſtrates may not make <hi>Penal Laws</hi> for Offences againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: for then upon that ground he may not make Laws for Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences againſt Second-Table-Commands, as <hi>Murther, Adultery, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ft, &amp;c.</hi> for the New Teſtament doth not preſcribe any. And therefore, on this account, ſome have been ſo wild, to think that no corporal puniſhments ſhould be inflicted under the Goſpel, by Chriſtian men.</p>
               <p>But 'tis generally agreed by all, That the natural and moral part of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (to wit) that which is founded on Reaſon and Moral Juſtice, is ſtill obligatory on all Nations; and 'tis certain, that a great part of the Judicial Law is but an Expoſition and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of the natural and moral Law of God: Hence moſt of the Penalties inflicted by that Law, for Offences againſt any of the Precepts of the moral Law, we may find that the reaſon and ground of the Penalty may in many things be drawn from the moral na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Crime, as well as from the Will of God preſcribing the kind of Penalty. Now it cannot be denied, that where the reaſon and ground of the Penalty, for ſuch and ſuch Offences, is natural and moral, there thoſe Penal Laws are ſo far ſtill in force, that they remain on Record, both as Precedents and Engagements on all Nations, to make Laws in conformity to them. And ſurely, where we cannot ſo clearly ſee the reaſon of the penalty, yet where the Offence againſt the Law of God is the ſame there the Will of God impoſing penalties, for ſuch and ſuch Offences againſt his Law, is the beſt Rule and Pattern for the Laws of all Magiſtrates in the world.</p>
               <p>Now, If the Abolition of the <hi>Jeuiſh</hi> Pedagogy, and their Civil State, for which theſe Penal Laws were more peculiarly adapted, doth not null the power of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, to make Penal Laws, for the Violation of Second-Table-Commands, as for <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Wheredom, Theft, &amp;c.</hi> Why ſhould it any more null his power to make Penal Laws, for the Violation of Firſt-Table-Commands, as for <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition, Blaſphemy, &amp;c.</hi> for the Firſt-Table-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands have ſtill the precedent Obligation to the Second; and the Violation of them have the ſame moral Obliquity and Guilt as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law? Therefore Laws to puniſh thoſe Sins, have the ſame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57754:8"/> Reaſon and moral Juſtice in them as the other: Hence it will follow that Magiſtrates are under equal Obligations to impoſe ſuch Laws as the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> But it will be further objected, That Jeſus Chriſt hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed, under the Goſpel, the Miniſtry of the word (which is the Spiritual Sword) for the propagating and maintaining the Chriſtian Religion: And Men are invited to believe and embrace this Religion upon free Choice and Election, and upon principles of pure Conviction and Conſcience, and not compelled or forced to it by the power of the Sword; and that 'tis not agreeable to the Goſpel Diſpenſation, that the Chriſtian Religion ſhould be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Temporal power, or men puniſhed for diſobedience to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> For anſwer, this miſtake of denying the Authority of the Civil Magiſtrate in the matters of Religion, comes to paſs, by not diſtinguiſhing between thoſe two diſtinct Offices, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and of the <hi>Magiſtracy;</hi> which are Offices of a different Order, that have each their peculiar Properties and Imployments, tho' both to the great and general end of the Glory of God, and alſo the Good of the Church: The Miniſterial Office is properly founded on Chriſts Commiſſion, as Mediator of the Church, to whom are committed the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, both of Doctrin and of Diſcipline; but the Office of the Magiſtracy is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Order, and founded on God's Law, as he is Rector of the World, to whom is committed the Sword of Juſtice, and that not only between man and man, but between God and man. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy therefore is not properly a Goſpel, but a moral Inſtitution. Now, as the Goſpel doth not abrogate, but on the contrary doth eſtabliſh the Obligations of the moral Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 13. ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it doth not null either the Office, or any part of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Duty of the Office of Magiſtracy, but on the contrary doth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and confirm it, as it doth all other matters of moral Duty and Religion.</p>
               <p>'Tis true alſo, that our Saviour only appointed the Miniſtry of the <hi>Word</hi> for the propagation of the Goſpel, for he came into the world in the quality of a Prophet and Miniſter, and ſo propagated his Religion, and in that Capacity commiſſionated and ſent forth his Apoſtles and Goſpel-Miniſters: He did not intermeddle with the Office of the Magiſtracy, but left that to ſtand on its own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, as founded on the Law and Ordinance of God; for tho' he were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57754:8"/> a King, yet his Kingdom were ſpiritual, and not of this world; and therefore as he took not the power of the Temporal Sword himſelf, (as he might have done upon Divine Right) ſo he gave no ſuch power to any of the Miniſterial Order.</p>
               <p>And we find alſo that God Almighty, in whoſe power are the Hearts of Kings and Magiſtrates, did not uſe their Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the promotion and advancement of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, at the firſt; which he might have done, by effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and converting them by his Grace, as well as others, and ſo inclining their Hearts to improve their Power and Office for his Glory, as was their Duty to do; but he did not, and that, no doubt, in great wiſdom, that ſo the Goſpel being propagated, by ſuch weak and contemptible Inſtruments as the Apoſtles were, without the concurrence of the Civil Power, yea, and againſt ſuch great oppoſition from them, might be given to the world one of the moſt convincing Evidences that could be, of the truth of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>But it doth not follow thence, but that it was then the Duty of Magiſtrates, even when they were Enemies to Chriſt, both to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and to imploy their Power for the Advancement of God's True Religion and VVorſhip, for this they were morally oblig'd to do from the nature of their Office. And therefore Chriſt's imploying the Goſpel-miniſters in a Miniſterial way, doth not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thoſe Obligations that lie upon tho Magiſtrate, by the moral Law of God, to take care for the Advancement and Security of True Religion; for ſeeing the Office of Magiſtracy is contiuned under the Goſpel, we need no New Teſtament-Precepts to inforce his Duty in this reſpect, which is incumbent on him, not immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by any Goſpel-precept, but by a previous Obligation, ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to the Goſpel-Miniſtry, which is moral and perpetual, inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in his very Office and Dignity; that having Authority from God, and being in his Stead in the world, ſhould imploy his power beſt for God's ſervice and glory.</p>
               <p>And as the Magiſtrate is not diſoblig'd to promote and preſerve True Religion under the Goſpel, from the office of the Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, imployed to that end, neither is it diſagreeable with the Goſpel Diſpenſation, that he ſhould do ſo, more than formerly under the Law; for the difference between the Law and the Goſpel doth not lie in any of the moral Obligations of Religion, but chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57754:9"/> in the Poſitive, and Typical, and Ceremonial part, which is now fulfilled by the Coming of Chriſt, and ſo done away: but the moral part is ſtill the ſame, as under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and thoſe few po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Doctrines and Inſtitutions, that are peculiar to the Goſpel, are all included in the moral Law; for the Firſt-Table Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments do comprehend all the Doctrines and Ordinances of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and require belief of them, and obedience to them; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the moral Law doth comprehend the whole Duty of man, for it requireth Belief in whatſoever God ſhall reveal, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to whatſoever He ſhall command.</p>
               <p>Now I argue thus; That if the whole Law of God be the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Rule of Laws and Magiſtracy, (as we noted before) then certainly the Magiſtrate is Keeper of both Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Law, or elſe he is Keeper of neither. Hence it will then follow, that all the Goſpel Inſtitutions, thus included in the Firſt-Table-Commands, are under the care of the Magiſtracy, as well as thoſe Duties that reſpect the Second-Table-Commands.</p>
               <p>Thus 'tis very clear, That the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel is bound by the Law of God to imploy his power and care for true Religion, and the VVorſhip of God. And if ſo, then he ought, no doubt, to make Laws for the promotion and ſupport of it, for that the power and office of Magiſtracy is exerted by Laws, to which Laws 'tis neceſſary that there be a Sanction of Penalties upon the Breach of them; for if the Magiſtrate have only a mandative and preceptive power in the matters of Religion, and not power to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict Penalties for the Violation of Laws, he may be ſaid to bear the Sword in vain in that reſpect. And 'tis neceſſary to Laws, that they be backed with Penalties, not only to further obedience, but alſo to maintain the honour of the Law, and the authority of the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>But as to the Magiſtrates forcing perſons to believe in Chriſt, this he cannot do, becauſe Faith is an Act of the Underſtanding and the VVill; but where the Faith of Chriſt is not generally profeſſed he may both require the Attendance of the Perſon on the publick preaching of the <hi>Word,</hi> and alſo prohibit and ſuppreſs all publick profeſſion and practice of Idolatry and falſe Religion: But this is not: the Caſe in ſuch Governments, where all have taken up the profeſſion of Chriſt and his true Religion, at leaſt in the ſpeculative and doctrinal part of it, and have vowed by Baptiſm to adhere to that Religion both in profeſſion and practice. Alſo where ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57754:9"/> have taken on them the Miniſterial Function in the Church, and thereby have obliged themſelves to the Duties of the ſame. In theſe caſes, doubtleſs, the Chriſtian Magiſtrate may, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good Kings, under the Old Teſtament, require and cauſe by good Laws, both Miniſters and People to do their reſpective Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Religion, and impoſe penalties for defections or neglects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the merit of the fault; and for grievous Offences againſt Religion, as <hi>Idolatry, Hereſie, Blaſphemy, &amp;c.</hi> when they are certain and apparent, may doubtleſs inflict corporal puniſhments, after the example of God's own Laws.</p>
               <p>And that the infliction of corporal puniſhments for great Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt Religion, is not diſagreeable with the Goſpel Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, appears plainly by the Examples of St. <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 5. 10. who uſing an extraordinary Authority, above that of the Miniſtry, did wonderfully put <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> to death, for <hi>Sacril. dge</hi> and <hi>Lying;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrook <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer with Blindneſs for oppoſing the Goſpel, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 11. which miraculous waies of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments were accommodated to that preſent ſtate of the Church, in the want of Chriſtian Magiſtrates to ſuccour and deſend it, who were then ſo far from maintaining the Intereſt of the Church, that they were the greateſt Enemies to it, and Perſecuters of it: But yet nevertheleſs thoſe Examples prove, that corporal puniſhments for great Offences againſt Religion, are conſiſtent with the Goſpel Diſpenſation.</p>
               <p>Thus, I hope, I have ſufficiently proved the power and duty of the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel, to promote and maintain by Laws the <hi>True Religion,</hi> and ſo paſs on to the Second Queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>QUEST. II. Whether it be lawful for the Chriſtian Magiſtrate to give a general Toleration of all Religions; or, what Liberty in Religion he ought to allow.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> TO this I anſwer in the Negative, That he may not give a general Toleration of all Religions: Put what hath been laid down a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d proved in Anſwer to the former Queſtion, may indeed ſerve for an Anſwer likewiſe in part both to this and the following Queſtions, which will be eaſily and plainly anſwered in the Negative, upon ſuppoſition of the Truth of the former Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57754:10"/> namely, That 'tis the Duty of the Magiſtrate to promote and maintain the True Religion: From thence it will follow, that he may neither give a general Toleration of all Religions, nor the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Conſent to ſuch a Toleration, or to the repealing the Laws that eſtabliſh and preſerve the True Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he may not give a general Toleration of all Religions;</hi> I urge therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the Inconſiſtency of giving ſuch a Toleration with his Duty to promote and maintain the True Religion, for thence it will follow, that he ought not (willingly at leaſt) to tolerate any but the True Religion; and that he ought alſo to endeavour by all expedient and lawful means, to ſuppreſs and exterminate all Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry &amp; Falſe Religion. And tho' (as we noted before) the Magiſtrate cannot force any without the Viſible Church to believe in Chriſt, yet no doubt 'tis his Duty, where the True Religion is not generally known and profeſt, not only to provide that the Ignorant and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous People may be well inſtructed in the True Religion, but alſo to prohibit and ſuppreſs the publick Profeſſion and Practice of Idolatry, Hereſie, Blaſphemy, and ſuch-like, as being ſo repugnant and prejudicial to the True Religion, which he is obliged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and maintain: But to give a Toleration of theſe, and of all Religions whatſoever, is ſo far from ſuppreſſing it, that 'tis not only an Allowance of it, but a kind of ſetting it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It may be further proved Unlawful, from the Command of God on the Magiſtracy of the Old Teſtament, to ſuppreſs all falſe Prophets, Teachers, and Idolaters, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 2, 6, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the Example of all good Kings and Magiſtrates, that did ſo, and are approved for ſo doing.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> From the great injury and hurt that the Cauſe of True Religion and the Church of God is like to receive by ſuch a Toleration, by giving occaſion to Satan by falſe Teachers, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the Church with the Seeds of Falſe Doctrines, and to corrupt the pure Worſhip of God, with Idolatry and Superſtition; which the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, as a Watchman over the Church, ſhould labour to prevent.</p>
               <p>This, in ſhort, might ſerve ſufficiently to demonſtrate the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs and great impiety of ſuch a Toleration, but becauſe a general Toleration under the ſpecious pretence of Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, hath been, and is a matter ſo vehemently argued for by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57754:10"/> I ſhall a little enquire into the nature and ground of this <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience</hi> pleaded for, by which I preſume, moſt underſtand nothing elſe, but an Exemption from the Obligation of all humane Laws in the matters of Religion; therefore I ſhall in the firſt place examine thoſe Grounds, upon which ſuch a Liberty of Conſcience ſeems to be claimed and pleaded for, which being found rotten and unſound, ſuch a Toleration will then further appear unlawful to be given by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. And then, Secondly, I ſhall further examin what that lawful Liberty is in the matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which of Divine Right ought to be allowed by the Magiſtrate to every Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Concerning ſuch a Liberty of Conſcience as is oppoſed to all human Laws, in matters of Religion, I ſhall enquire into theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What Obligation of humane Laws there is upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in the things of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether an Erroneous Conſcience do exempt from the Obligation of Juſt Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether the conſideration of an Erroneous Conſcience, under the infliction of a Penalty on ſuch a Perſon to be Unjuſt: Of theſe very briefly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the Obligation of humane Laws upon the Conſcience, we acknowledge, that 'tis only the Law of God, that doth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately bind the Conſcience, becauſe the Conſcience is only ſubject to God, and under his Authority alone; the Magiſtrate hath only power over the Body and outward practice, but yet nevertheleſs the Conſcience is bound by the Law of God to obey all lawful and juſt Commands of the Magiſtrate. Now thoſe Laws of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate about Religion, that are but the Inforcement of God's own Commands and Inſtitutions, have a double Obligation upon the Conſcience, both by Vertue of the immediate Divine Authority ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing them, as alſo from the Command of God requiring Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to humane Authority chiefly in ſuch things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Neither doth an Erroneous Conſcience exempt from the Obligation of Juſt Laws; for tho' every man have a Judgment of private diſcretion in and about what he ought to do in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet if he judge erroneouſly of what is juſtly required by Laws to be done, his Judgment and erroneous Conſcience therein, doth not exempt him from the Obligation of thoſe Commands; for tho'
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57754:11"/>
'tis true, that he ſins in acting againſt an erroneous Conſcience, yet he ought to lay it down, and then to act; and if it be a neceſſary Duty, he ſins if he do not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Neither will the infliction of a Penalty be unjuſt, that is laid on a Perſon, for doing or omitting that which he is led to by an erroneous Conſcience: This is the grand miſtake about <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> that becauſe every man hath a liberty to judge for himſelf, what he ought to do in Religion, that therefore, if he judge erroneouſly, yet he ought to be tolerated in ſo doing; No, he ought to lay down his erroneous Conſcience, or elſe, as he ſins, ſo he juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffers from Authority in following the Dictates of it: But, that he ſins in following an erroneous Conſcience, I think no one of ſenſe will deny; for if it be lawful for a man to act in Religion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Dictates of his own Conſcience, when 'tis erroneous, then 'tis lawful for him to commit <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſpeak <hi>Blaſphemy, &amp;c.</hi> if his Conſcience lead him to it. Therefore, if the Plea of an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Conſcience will not free a Man from the Guilt of thoſe Sins that he is led into by it, then certainly it will not exempt a Man from the Juſt Obligation of Puniſhment, from the Magiſtrate, for thoſe Sins, who is the Avenger of God againſt all evil Doers: And the Magiſtrate doth offer no Violence to Conſcience, by either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Obedience, or exacting the Penalties for Diſobedience to Juſt and Righteous Commands; for if Mens erroneous Conſciences will not ſuffer them to Obey, 'tis no force upon Conſcience for the outward Man to bear the Penalty.</p>
               <p>But beſides, If ſuch a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> be due to every man, as ſhall exempt him from the Obligation of all humane Laws in the matters of Religion, it will then follow, that the Magiſtrate hath no Authority in the matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſo it will null the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt part of his Office; for where there is no Obligation to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there can be no Authority to Command, thoſe being Correla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and cannot be one without the other.</p>
               <p>But to conclude this particular, If it be ſo as we have proved, that the Conſcience be bound by ſuch humane Laws, the matter of which is the Inforcement of God's own Commands and Inſtitutions, and that if an erroneous Conſcience doth not exempt a Man from the Obligation of ſuch Laws, nor render the Penalty inflicted for breaking of them to be Unjuſt, then certainly there is no ſuch <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience</hi> as an Exemption from all humane Laws about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57754:11"/> due to any Chriſtian, and therefore ought not to be granted by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I proceed now to the ſecond thing propoſed, to wit, What that lawful Liberty is in the matters of Religion, which of Divine Right ought to be Allowed by the Magiſtrate; for tho' we have aſſerted and proved the Duty and Power of the Magiſtrate, to make Laws for the promotion and maintenance of True Religion, yet we may not think that the Magiſtrate can by Laws intrench up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of the Rights, Liberties, and Priviledges, which of Divine Right do belong to the Chriſtian Religion, which he is obliged to maintain every Chriſtian in the Enjoyment of: Or, That any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Power hath ſuch an exorbitant and unlimited Authority of impoſing Rights and Ceremonies on the Church as they think good; which Principle hath been the ground of ſo many Corruptions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and indeed upon which Principle may be brought upon the Chriſtian Religion, by the reſtraint of <hi>Liberty</hi> in indifferent things, and the Impoſition of Ceremonies, a greater Yoke and Burthen than was impoſed by God's own Law. But we may not think that God hath now freed the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> under the Goſpel, from the Bondage of his own Ceremonies, and yet left them under a humane Power to impoſe what they think good.</p>
               <p>But we deſire, that what is ſaid on this Subject by way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, may not be interpreted a preſcribing to Authority, or limiting their Power; and therefore we humbly conceive, that the Magiſtrate hath Power in the matters of Religion, to impoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which is lawful, certain, and neceſſary. Hence then he may not injoyn in Religion things that are Either,
<list>
                     <item>1. Sinful.</item>
                     <item>2. Doubtful.</item>
                     <item>3. Meerly Indifferent.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Not <hi>things Sinful:</hi> This, I think, will be acknowledged by all, That no humane Power can lawfully require to be done that which is in it ſelf <hi>ſinful.</hi> And if any ſuch Laws are made, they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be void in themſelves, as to any Obligation to Obedience, having not the proper matter of Laws, which muſt alwaies be ſome uſeful Good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Not things <hi>Doubtful</hi> and Uncertain in Religion; and ſuch things we call <hi>Doubtful</hi> and Uncertain, that really in themſelves and in the Judgment of many learned and good Men, have no appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Foundation in the Word of God; for the Magiſtrate can make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57754:12"/> Laws in the matters of Religion, only of ſuch things as Chriſt hath commanded, and to do them decently and orderly, becauſe there is but one Legiſlator and Law-giver in and over the Church, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Jam.</hi> 4. 18. And humane Authority hath no proper Dictato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Legiſlative Power, but only a Miniſtratory and Directive one, in the things of Religion; therefore whatever the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in Religion, muſt be the obſervation of the Laws of Chriſt in the Church, and not his own Laws: for the ſtate of the Church is not like a Civil Body, that humane Laws are the conſtitutive form of it; but the Church and all its Laws, Priviledges, and Liberties, are all ſounded on the Word of God. Thus, as under the Law, all that Power which the Magiſtrate then had about Religion, was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and limitted by the Word of God, thoſe things which God had inſtituted and appointed in his Worſhip to be done, he was to take care for the due obſervation of it, but was not to add thereto, nor diminiſh from it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 32. So under the Goſpel, all the Power of Magiſtrates in the matters of Religion, is in ſuch things as are plainly preſcribed in the Word of God, or by evident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence deducible from it; and what is not ſo, may be called a thing <hi>Doubtful</hi> and Uncertain at the beſt, and therefore ſhould not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Nor in things <hi>meerly Indifferent:</hi> By things <hi>ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fferent,</hi> I mean things not neceſſary, nor required by any Divine Law. Now there is a two-fold neceſſity of things, the one Natural and Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical, the other Circumſtantial or Accidental only; and of <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> things, I call that ſo, that is Intrinſical and in its own nature <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> yet ſuch indifferent things by reaſon of circumſtances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout neceſſary things, or by Accident, may become either inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and alſo ſcandalous, and ſo unlawful, or they may become expedient, and ſo circumſtantially neceſſary. Now that, in Religion, that intrinſically and in its own nature is neceſſary, or elſe is nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary, by reaſon of Circumſtance or Accident, is the only proper matter of Laws; &amp; what is not ſuch, I call a thing <hi>meerly Indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſuch things ſhould not be put into Laws that are either, 1. <hi>Meerly Indifferent,</hi> 2. Much leſs when ſuch indifferent things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>become inexpedient; and, 3. Leaſt of all, when they become ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such things about Religion that are in their own nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and have no Circumſtantial neceſſity attending it that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a Reſtraint, is that wherein Chriſtians ought to have their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57754:12"/> liberty, and not to be reſtrained by Laws: becauſe if Authority can reſtrain Chriſtian Liberty, further than in things neceſſary, barely upon their own Authority and Will; they may upon the ſame Foundation take off all liberty in things indifferent. But this they cannot do juſtly, without wrong, becauſe liberty in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent is a Branch of that Chriſtian Liberty we have by the Goſpel, and is an Appendix to the very Eſſence of the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 23. Now, as the Magiſtrate cannot juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive any Man of any of his Civil Rights and Properties, without juſt reaſon and cauſe; much leſs may he deprive us of any of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rights and Priviledges, without a juſt and neceſſary cauſe; and liberty in things indifferent, being one of theſe Rights, we ought therefore to be preſerved in the enjoyment of it, and not to be brought under a reſt raint therein, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any thing;</hi> by <hi>all things,</hi> he means things indifferent and lawful on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not neceſſary, yet would not be brought under the power of any of theſe. Which proves, that no Chriſtian ſhould be brought by Laws, under a power either of doing or not doing things in their own nature and uſe only indifferent and lawful: And the Scripture in divers places aſſerts the liberty of Chriſtians in things indifferent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 3, 5. And we ſee alſo that our Saviour vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated his Diſciples, in uſing their liberty in the forbearance of a thing in its own nature indifferent, tho' injoined by Authority, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. which proves alſo, that Authority, as it may not impoſe things meerly indifferent, ſo cannot make them neceſſary when impoſed. And indeed, if it had been lawful to reſtrain Chriſtians of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in things indifferent, how eaſie had it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to have ſilenc'd all Diſputes about the obſervation of Meats and Days, and ſuchlike indifferent things, by determinining the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Chriſtians in thoſe things on one ſide or other, by ſome Law or Canon, and by directing the Church in after-times in the like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to make Laws in order to heal and take off ſuch Differences; but becauſe he did not, but on the contrary doth ſo frequently aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the liberty of every Chriſtian in things indifferent, to uſe with prudence and charity; it follows therefore, that ſuch Laws ſhould not be made, which violate and infringe Chriſtian l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> But much leſs may indifferent things be impoſed, when they become inexpedient; which they do in Religion, when they are unprofitable, and tend not to Ediſication. Thus the Apoſtle,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57754:13"/> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 23. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but all things are not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: all things are lawful for me, but all things edifie not.</hi> Where the latter Clauſe expounds the former; ſuch lawful things as do not edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, are not expedient, and therefore not to be put into Laws, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all humane Authority, in the matters of Religion, is only for edification, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8. 13. 10. therefore ſuch Conſtitutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion ceaſe to oblige, when they ceaſe to edifie, becauſe the Obligation to obey in the things of Religion, can extend no farther than the Authority to command; which we ſee is only things for edification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Leaſt of all ſhould indifferent things be impoſed, when they become ſcandalous, for then the uſe of them becomes in moſt caſes unlawful and ſinful, and therefore much more unlawful to be impoſed by Laws. And indeed, this is the great reaſon why Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things ſhould rarely be impoſed by Laws, becauſe Scandal is ſo apt to riſe out of the uſe of Indifferent things; and therefore we are to uſe our liberty, or to deny it, according as ſuch or ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances require, for the avoiding of Scandal; for we may not do a thing meerly Indifferent, to the Scandal of our Brother, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 13. <hi>If Meat make my Brother to offend, I will eat no Fleſh while the world ſtands, leſt I make my Brother to offend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Authority therefore cannot juſtly command ſuch an indifferent thing to be done, when 'tis apparent thereby Scandal will follow, for this will be to make void the Commandments of God by the Commands of Men; the Command of God is, <hi>Give no offence,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 32. and this Command of God is Obligatory on Rulers, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws in Indifferent things; as well as on private Chriſtians, in their practice towards each other. If Rulers therefore command ſuch an Indifferent thing to be done, which cannot be done by many without a doubting Conſcience, they do in effect command that which is evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 23. <hi>He that doubteth, is damned if he eat;</hi> and yet this was but in an indifferent thing: If Authority had then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to eat, (and ſo in the like caſe) it had been to command a Scandal, and ſo unlawful. 'Tis true, if it be a neceſſary Duty by a Divine Law, that is commanded by Authority, there if Scandal follow, 'tis Scandal taken, and not given, and the fault is wholly in him that takes the Offence; but if it be an unneceſſary Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing, 'tis Scandal given by the Authority that impoſeth it.</p>
               <p>And alſo hereby they not only give Scandal to the Doubting, but oblige all others, as much as they can, by the practice of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differences,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57754:13"/> to give Scandal alſo; for to ſay, that humane Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty makes an indifferent thing, that in it ſelf hath no neceſſary uſe, to become neceſſary, in the caſe of Scandal, is to make the Laws of Men to ſuperſede the Law of God; No certainly, if the thing were really ſcandalous, antecedent to the command, or the uſe of it would be ſo, were it not commanded, there no humane Authority can put ſuch a neceſſity into an indifferent thing, as to make it neceſſary to be done when Scandal follows; becauſe the Obligation to avoid Scandal in indifferent things, being a moral Duty, will ſuperſede any Obligation, that reſults from the Command of Authority in ſuch indifferent things: for this is but a meer Ritual, and Rituals muſt give place to Morals.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, that ſuch Indifferent things being unneceſſary in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> much more, if inexpedient and ſcandalous, ought not to be impoſed by Laws. But yet we do not hereby plead for ſuch a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in Religion, as is oppoſed to things in Religion, either nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary in their own nature, or neceſſary by reaſon of ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. And thus Indifferent things, that ſerve for the ordering the Worſhip of God in decent and comely manner, according to the Apoſtle's Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. are ſo far lawful to be impoſed, as they are expedient and neceſſary to thoſe ends; for all the Power of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority in the matters of Religion, beſides impoſing what God hath commanded in his Word, is only in ordering what God has ſo commanded to be done in decent and comely manner, and to edification: and as ſuch things appertaining to God's Worſhip are neceſſary in their general nature, as <hi>Time, Place, &amp;c.</hi> ſo in their Particulars, when they are indifferent in their own nature, yet do, by reaſon of Circumſtances and Accidents, become neceſſary to be determined, they then loſe their nature of Indifferences, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary, antecedent to any Impoſition of them by Authority.</p>
               <p>But yet nevertheleſs, the determination of ſuch Indifferent things ſhould not be impoſed by Laws in the caſe of Scand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, unleſs in theſe Caſes, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Unleſs the neceſſity of impoſing them be great, apparent, and certain, and not pretended only. 2. Unleſs the Good that is brought to Religion by the impoſition of Indifferent things, be not greater than the Evil of Scandal it brings with it. 3. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Good End they are neceſſary for, cannot be by ſome other means ſo well attained, without ſo great a ſcandal: But where is no ſuch neceſſary Good, or but little, comparative to the Evil of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal; or if the Good End deſigned may be by other means attained,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57754:14"/> without ſo great Scandal, there certainly in reaſon Scandal ſhould be avoided, becauſe 't<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſo great an Evil, and ſo much condemned in the Word of God, in the uſe of Indifferent things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obj.</label> But that which is uſually objected againſt liberty in Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, is the Judgment of Authority, ſeeing them neceſſary; for, ſay they, <hi>Who ſhall judge of what is neceſſary in Religion, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Laws, but Rulers themſelves?</hi> For if a liberty be allowed to the People, to judge of the lawfulneſs or neceſſity of what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and accordingly to obey or not obey, as they judge of them; this will overthrow all Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> The Magiſtrate hath a publick Authoritative Judgment in what they are to require, and the People have a private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Diſcretion in what they are to do and obey; and tho' both theſe may be abuſed, yet both may very well ſtand together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either overthrowing the Authority of Government, or diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Obligation to Obedience; but very ill conſequences will follow on denying either; for if we deny the Judgment of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to command, this indeed is to overthrow all Humane Power to command in the matters of Religion; and to deny the Peoples Judgment of private Diſcretion, is both to take off the uſe of their Reaſon, and to lay upon them a neceſſity of ſinning; for if only the Judgment and Will of Authority be the Rule of Laws, or the Obligation to Obedience, it will then follow, that we are bound to obey whatever they command, tho' ſinful, if they judge it not ſo: But as the Magiſtrate's authoritative Judgment doth not bind to Obedience, when he judgeth erroneouſly in that which is required, ſo tho Peoples Judgment of private diſcretion doth not diſoblige them from Obedience, nor render them inculpable when they judg erroneouſly of what is required: Therefore each party, both Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Subject, ſhould be very careful to judge aright, namely, the Ruler, in judging nothing fit to be commanded in Religion, but what is evidently lawful and neceſſary, and then their Commands are binding: And the Subjects ſhould be very careful, not to judge erroneouſly of the Commands of Authority, for then they juſtly ſuffer for Diſobedience. Each party indeed muſt judge for ſo much as concerns themſelves and their own Duty, both <hi>Authority</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, and the <hi>People</hi> in obeying; but the Judgment of neither doth change the nature of the things themſelves, ſo as to make that lawful and neceſſary, or unlawful and not neceſſary, that are not really ſo in themſelves.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57754:14"/> But we find, that this Argument of enforcing Obedience in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, meerly from the Judgment of <hi>Authority,</hi> is never made uſe of, but when men want ſufficient force of Argument from the matter of the things themſelves, then they flee to the Judgment and Obligation of <hi>Authority</hi>-commanding, which indeed will equally hold in <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf, upon ſuppoſition, that the <hi>Authority,</hi> either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, be a lawful <hi>Authority</hi> that commands.</p>
               <p>But this Objection is of no force in ſuch things, wherein 'tis acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, That there is no neceſſity in the nature of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, why they ſhould be impoſed; beſides the will of Authority commanding it, there the obligation to Obedience is urged meerly from the will of Authority requiring it, and not their Judgment of the neceſſary uſefulneſs of ſuch things. But what force and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the meer will of Authority hath in the matters of Religion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſound Reaſon from the Matter required, we ſhall have occaſion to ſay ſomewhat unto under the next Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Thus I have endeavoured with all poſſible Brevity to demonſtrate what that lawful Liberty in the Matters of Religion is, which the Chriſtian Magiſtrate ſhould juſtly allow to every man: but to allow an unlimited Toleration in the practice of Religion, is to run into the contrary Extream, of impoſing unneceſſary and doubtful things; and 'tis to be ſuppoſed, that much of that miſtake that hath been about a Toleration, hath come to paſs, by not duly conſidering this Golden Mean of <hi>Liberty</hi> only in unneceſſary things in Religion, between the two Extreams of unneceſſary Impoſitions, and an unlimited Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but as the former is bad, being againſt Chriſtian Liberty and Charity, yet the latter is much worſe, becauſe it tends to ſubvert the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> and to overthrow all Government in the Matters of Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>QUEST. III. Whether it be lawful for Subjects to give their Actual Conſent to a general Toleration.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> TO which I anſwer in the Negative, That they may not. And indeed there will be occaſion to ſay but little in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Queſtion; for having before proved, in Anſwer to the foregoing Queſtion, That the Magiſtrate <hi>may not</hi> lawfully allow ſuch a Toleration; it will thence follow, That the Subject may not conſent to it, for by conſenting to that which is unlawfully done by others, we become partly Guilty of the Evil ſo done.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57754:15"/>
               <p>But yet it may be proper for us under this Queſtion, to enquire, Whether it may come under the Charge of an Aſſent to ſuch a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to practiſe ſome Liberty in the Exerciſe of Religion that is reſtrained by Laws, when 'tis allowed by ſuch a Toleration.</p>
               <p>I ſhall anſwer this in theſe Three Particulars:
<list>
                     <item>1. That ſuch a liberty in Religion, as conſiſts only in an Exemption from the Obligation of things in their own nature unneceſſary, doubtful, or ſcandalous, may lawfully be practiſed, though the ſame be reſtrained by Laws.</item>
                     <item>2. That there is no Scandal given by the practice of ſuch a Liberty.</item>
                     <item>3. Nor any Aſſent thereby to a general Toleration.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſuch a Liberty in Religion as conſiſts only in an exemption or omiſſion of things in their own nature unneceſſary, doubtful, or ſcandalous, may lawfully be practiſed, tho' the ſame be reſtrained by Laws, becauſe the matter of ſuch Laws cannot be Obligatory upon the Conſcience, by vertue of any Law of God, there being no Divine Law upon which to bottom &amp; authorize ſuch Laws, which is neceſſary in all Laws about Religion, as we have before noted. And wherein there is no Authority to require, therein can be no obligation from the Command to obey, and the meer will of Authority can lay no Obligation in the matters of Religion; but much more when any humane Laws about Indifferent things do interfere with the Law of God, of avoiding Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal in ſuch Indifferent things, there certainly ſuch Laws do loſe their force and obligation, becauſe the obligation from humane Authority ceaſeth, and becomes void, when a previous and greater obligation to the Law of God is to take place: by which we are obliged not to do that about Religion, which being in it ſelf not neceſſary, is in its uſe ſcandalous to many. And indeed, ſuch Laws that enforce the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch things, doubtful and ſcandalous in Religion, ſeem to loſe the force of Laws, and to be void in themſelves, having not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Matter, nor anſwering the end of Law; and therefore a liberty in omitting ſuch things, tho' injoined by Laws, is lawful to be practiſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And that there is no Scandal given by the practice of ſuch a Liberty; for it may be ſaid, That tho' there be no obligation, either from the matter of the things required, or from Authority requiring it, to uſe ſome Indifferent things; yet they being Indifferent, we are bound to uſe them, to avoid Scandal to Authority, and to others that will be ſcandalized by our omitting them. And therefore upon this ground divers learned Conformiſts have thought it lawful to omit the Ceremonies injoined by <hi>Laws,</hi> when Scandal doth not follow, being neither neceſſary in themſelves, nor from the Command of Authority,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57754:15"/> any further than in the caſe of Scandal. Here we may obſerve, That ſuch as eſteem ſuch things not meerly Indifferent, but Doubtful in themſelves, if not Unlawful, cannot be obliged to uſe them to avoid Scandal to others: But if they are but <hi>meerly Indifferent</hi> in their own nature, yet proving <hi>Scandalous</hi> to many, and upon ſuppoſition of the Truth of what we have proved, that there is no Obligation from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in ſuch Indifferent things, when they become ſcandalous, it will then follow, that there can be no ſcandal given by omitting them; tho' Scandal be taken, or tho' in the uſe of an unneceſſary thing in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we really give Scandal, yet by the omiſſion of it is now given, tho' Scandal may be taken thereupon: becauſe Scandal given, ariſeth either out of the omiſſion of ſomething neceſſary to be done, or doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either unlawful, or unneceſſary tho' lawful. Now, if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Authority doth not make that in Religion not neceſſary in it ſelf, to become neceſſary when Scandal follows, as we have proved it cannot do, then certainly no Scandal is given by omitting ſuch unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things. For this we have a parallel Inſtance, in our Saviour's juſtifying his Diſciples in omitting a lawful, but an unneceſſary Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, tho' injoined by lawful Authority; notwithſtanding the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſces</hi> were ſcandalized by it, namely, in omitting to waſh before Meat, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
               <p>Therefore it being thus lawful and neceſſary, to omit ſuch indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things in Religion as are doubtful and ſcandalous, but yet alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to do and perform the eſſential and neceſſary parts of Divine Worſhip, the Practice of Chriſtians then, in keeping to all the nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary part of Proteſtant Doctrin and Worſhip, omitting only that which is in it ſelf unneceſſary, and in its uſe doubtful and ſcandalous, cannot juſtly be condemned as unlawful or ſcandalous: for herein they do but ſave and improve their own Right and Liberty, which they have by vertue of the Divine Law, without reſpect to the obligation of ſuch Laws, as either reſtrain a neceſſary Duty, or require an unneceſſary Ceremony. And the doing of a neceſſary Duty, and the omitting an unneceſſary Circumſtance, doth not render a man culpable of giving Scandal, the Scandal may perhaps be taken, or follow thereupon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence it follows, that this Liberty uſed in Religion ss no practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Aſſent to a general Toleration; for there being nothing in this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice granted thereby, but what was an original Right, antecedent, and without reſpect to ſuch a Toleration, it cannot follow, that Chriſtians thus uſing their liberty in the exerciſe of all the Eſſentials of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</hi> omitting only ſuch things, <hi>different</hi> and <hi>doubtful,</hi> cannot be ſaid to give any practical or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the lawfulneſs of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57754:16"/> Toleration of all Religions, becauſe the ground and reaſon of the Exerciſe of this Liberty is not founded on the Toleration, but both on the lawfulneſs and obligation of the Duty ſo to practiſe, without reſpect to ſuch a Toleration.</p>
               <p>Much leſs is it any practical Aſſent to a ſuppoſed power in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate, to diſpenſe with ſuch Laws as are of known uſe and neceſſity, to the ſupport of the Fundamentals both of the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> for tho' we ſhould grant, that the Supream Magiſtrate may diſpenſe with the obſervation of things <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> and <hi>doubtful</hi> in Religion, tho' injoined by Laws, as well as from the Penalties impoſed for omitting them, and that when the ſupream Law of Piety and Charity require it; it will not follow thence, that he may diſpence with all Laws that require both the profeſſion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of True Religion in the Eſſentials of Doctrin and Worſhip, and that prohibit <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Falſe Religion,</hi> and give a general Toleration of all Religions. I hope that all true Proteſtants, that accept their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty only in an exemption from ſuch things <hi>indifferent</hi> and <hi>doubtful</hi> in Religion, do utterly diſown the lawfulneſs of ſuch a Toleration, or of any ſuch power in the Supream Magiſtrate, to diſpence with the Laws: thoſe that through Ignorance or Errour have profeſſed any actual Conſent to it, are much to be pittied and blamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>QUEST. IV. Whether it be lawful for Subjects to Conſent to the Repealing thoſe Laws, that Eſtabliſh and Preſerve the True Chriſtian Religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> I Anſwer, That they may not, but that which hath been proved under the foregoing Queſtions, hath anticipated much of that might be ſaid in Anſwer to this; for the force of this Queſtion loſeth its ſtrength, upon ſuppoſition of the Truth of the former Hypotheſis, and needs little to be ſaid in Anſwer to it; for 'tis eaſie to ſee, that if it be the Magiſtrate's Duty, and ſo eſpecially the Duty of the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power to maintain the True Religion, 'tis then their Duty to maintain thoſe Laws, that both eſtabliſh, and are neceſſary to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of it, becauſe the Magiſtrate's Office and Power is exer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by Laws.</p>
               <p>Now thoſe Laws are either ſuch as require the profeſſion &amp; practice of the True Religion, or ſuch as prohibit and puniſh the profeſſion and exerciſe of Falſe Religion; neither of which may be lawfully repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, unleſs better Laws for the Security and Eſtabliſhment of True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be firſt provided: for by repealing the Laws that eſtabliſh the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57754:16"/> profeſſion and exerciſe of the True Religion, the Magiſtrate diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his care and regard for the Church of God, and ſo fruſtrates and makes void one of the ſpecial ends of his Office, and likewiſe betrays the Cauſe of Religion to the Rapine and Violence of its open and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemies.</p>
               <p>And then alſo the repealing the Laws that prohibit Falſe Religion and Idolatry, is not only an Allowance of it, but a conſtructive ſetting it up, at leaſt becoming partly guilty of it. Hence is that Rule in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, <hi>Cujus manu eſt ne quid fiat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i deputatur cum jain fit: In whoſe hand and power it is, that an Evil Act be not done, to them 'tis imputed if it be done.</hi> And this Rule doth moſt properly reſpect Magiſtrates, and thoſe that have Power over others, who are truly ſaid to be guilty of that Evil, which they are able by good Laws to prevent, and do not. And therefore, that Magiſtrates ought to prohibit, at leaſt the publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and exerciſe of Idolatry and Falſe Religion, was, no doubt, the ground of thoſe good Laws which prohibit the ſame, which our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with ſo much zeal for the Truth of the Proteſtant Religion, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt Popery and Idolatry: But with what zeal for, or ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity unto the Proteſtant Religion, they may now be repealed, I do not underſtand.</p>
               <p>If then it be not morally lawful for the Legiſlative Power to repeal thoſe Laws that eſtabliſh and preſerve the Proteſtant Religion, I need not then further prove, that it is not lawful for the People to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto; which will thence follow. But I ſhall conclude all, by making ſome ſhort Anſwer to Three of theſe Arguments, which I judg are the moſt ſpecious that are urged for repealing the Penal Laws; and thoſe alſo are of ſo little weight, that there need little to be ſaid in anſwer to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis ſaid, That the Penal Laws made againſt <hi>Popery</hi> have been perverted from their proper end and uſe againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to oppreſs and perſecute <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> for Diſſenting only in matters of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Ceremony in Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> But this is not the fault of the Laws, but of thoſe that had the executive Power, and was ſo done (as now appears plainly) to ſerve the Deſign of <hi>Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> then carrying on: But tho' the Peral Laws have been ſo perverted, yet ſeeing it appears, that they are of ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſe, for the Security of the Proteſtant Religion againſt Popery, they may not for that reaſon be repealed. But as for thoſe Laws that impoſe Penalties on Proteſtants, adhering to all the eſſential and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary parts of Proteſtant Doctrin and Worſhip, but upon ſcruple of Conſcience, diſſent in ſome Matters of Circumſtance and Ceremony
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57754:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> in Religion, which to them are doubtful and uncertain; 'tis to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that the Wiſdom, Piety, and Charity of another Parliament may either give a greater latitude in the terms of Church-Communion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Proteſtants, or abate the rigour of thoſe Laws, that impoſe Penalties for Nonconformity only in ſuch matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis further alledg'd by ſome, That there are ſome Abuſes and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Religion, ſtill remaining in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that all thoſe Penal Laws eſtabliſh and confirm them, and require full Conformity to them, as to the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part of Religion, upon pain of Penalties annexed to thoſe Laws, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhould be repealed for the ſake of thoſe Abuſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Tho' we ſuppoſe there are Abuſes and Corruptions about the Circumſtances of Religion, confirmed by the ſame Laws, whereby the ſubſtantial and neceſſary part is confirmed; yet it will not follow therefore, that for the ſake of thoſe Abuſes, thoſe Laws ſhould be made void, that confirm the eſſential part, unleſs (as we ſaid before) better Laws could firſt be obtained, that might at leaſt ſo well Secure the eſſential part, becauſe a leſſer Evil is to be choſen, to wit, the burthen of thoſe Abuſes, rather than a greater, namely, The Overthrow of the whole Frame of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and the Introduction of <hi>Popery:</hi> Therefore where a leſs-neceſſary Good cannot yet be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto, there the moſt neceſſary Good already attained muſt be preſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis further objected, That thoſe Laws never did, nor never will anſwer their End, of bringing all Perſons into an Uniformity in Religion, for which they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this is the main Reaſon given by ſome for Repealing them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> To which may be anſwered, That the ſame is objected by <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the Scriptures themſelves, of being the Rule of Faith, that they never anſwered their End of reconciling Differences in Religion. And indeed, upon as good grounds it may be ſaid of the Law of God, That it is not the Rule of Life, becauſe it doth not attain its End of being ſuch, for that all Men will not be ruled by it.</p>
               <p>But for further Anſwer, Thoſe Laws have attained their End ſo far hitherto, as to ſupport and maintain the eſſential and neceſſary parts of Proteſtant Doctrin and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, againſt the prevalency of <hi>Popery,</hi> for which end moſt of the Penal Laws are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially intended; but that they have not alſo attained their end of procuring Unity and Uniformity in leſſer matters, relating to Modes and Ceremonies in Divine Worſhip, hath been doubtleſs the too much overdoing, by the Impoſition of ſuch things unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and doubtful in Religion; which will perpetuate Diviſions to the World's end, whilſt they are made neceſſary Conditions of Communion amongſt Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>But alas, either Unity, or Diverſity of Opinion and Practice in ſuch matters as theſe are, is not of that moment and concernment that ſome men imagine, that lay ſo much ſtreſs and weight upon things of Ceremony and Circumſtance, and ſo little value the Subſtantial and Great things of Religion. The principal Bond of Chriſtian Unity is an Unity in the profeſſion and practice of the Proteſtant Faith, to the preſervation of which, thoſe Laws are eſpecially to be eſteemed as uſeful; and therefore ſhould not be repealed, unleſs better Laws, conducing more effectually to thoſe great ends of Religion, can be made and provided.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
